So if you have a look at this inheritance class, the inheritance situation that we have
currently, you will just see that it's a one dimensional behavior and that's not where
the true power of inheritance lies.
So what you see is we have a class human and then we have three different methods with
their own bodies, right?
And then inside Ranjith, we, because we extend from human, all of the methods coming down
from human are now present in Ranjith, as they are in Shweta and Sneha, but when you call
them with the subclass object like Ranjith.breathe it at work and Shweta.breathe walk and dance
and maybe Sneha.breathe, you get the same behavior as was defined in the super type in the
super class human and that just makes it as a said one dimensional in the real world, you
don't see that right every human now be Ranjith, Shweta, Sneha, Usman or Ravi, they all inherit the
super class that is human, but then they can have there and there they in fact have their
own way of eating, own way of walking, own way of running and smiling and crying then other
humans, right?
So because that makes them unique, that makes them a different human, otherwise we would just
have been like Robos and even in 2026 Robos are not the same, all Robos would not be the
same thanks to AI, right?
So for having this different kind of behavior, although the methods are the same in inside
every class, right?
But we don't want this one dimensional static kind of a behavior that is where polymorphism
steps in again and you know that the first way of implementing polymorphism in Java is method
overloading that we already covered, the second way is what we are going to talk about
here and that is when polymorphism and inheritance would work together and make your core
more stronger and future rich, right?
Two core concepts of object oriented programming working in tandem with each other, right?
And that is inheritance and polymorphism and the second way to implement in that is polymorphism
in Java is method overriding, the first one method overloading, the second one method
over riding and for method overriding to work, first inheritance has to be interplay, right?
And you see that we have inheritance here, but we want different behavior with different
classes, right?
And what happens with method overriding is that is again one face many forms, now Ranjit,
the subclass of human has a choice.
Now what is that choice?
The choice is with Ranjit whether he wants to have eat, walk and breathe in the same
way as every human does or he wants to carve out a different way of eating, walking and
breathing that is unique to Ranjit and Shweta has the same choice as well as Sneha and
as all as all humans.
Now so that concept is called method overriding and what does that mean?
That means that when a method in the subclass has the same signature and you can write
it in brackets except a few exceptional scenarios where the signature might be different,
but it is still overriding and we'll have a look at those exceptional scenarios in some
time.
But for now, without them, I'll tell you that is when a subclass has this has the same
signature, when a subclass method has the same signature as of a method in the superclass.
The subclass method then is said to be overriding the superclass method and at that time
we call the subclass method the overriding method and the superclass method as the over-ridden
method, right?
I'll again repeat for you, that is when a method in the subclass has exactly the same signature
as of the method in the superclass, this concept is called method overriding, right?
It just gives you that is the subclass and option to have its own particular unique behavior.
Let's go on and do that.
What I'll do is in class Ranjit, Ranjit had a choice whether he wants to breathe, eat
and walk in the generic human way or in his own way.
He did not take the choice, that's fine because overriding is a choice, all right?
Shweta, see, hasn't took the choice either but now she does, so in addition to dance
which is her own method, what she decides is I want to have my own way of eating.
In human way of breathe, eat and walk, these methods can be over-ridden now, so I'll
just put in a South here, that makes it clear for you, I'll say Shweta's own way of eating.
Similarly, Shweta shakes the choice with walk and does the same that as a South, Shweta's
own style of walking because you would just imagine this, this is a very good example as
I've been telling you that is if you just have a look at from your window and my window
is to the right side right now when I'm recording this video for you.
So if I have a look at downstairs, there's a person walking and I can, I can make it out
from let's say fifth or sixth hole, that is that person is my friend, not some stranger
because he has a unique particular way of walking, right?
Because what is this?
This is, everyone of us has the same walk but we can define it in its own way and this
is just a South here but in the real world perspective, how humans would walk, you would
put that definition here, right?
So but Shweta takes the choice to have her own way of eating, takes the choice of having
her own way of walking but decides to breathe in the same way every human does, right?
Doesn't override breathe but does override eat and walk, why do I say override?
Because there was already a version of eat which came down from human, there was already
a version of walk which came down from human but now you can have multiple methods again
in the same class, right?
Because that eat and walk are invisible but they're still there, now you've eaten walk,
right?
It's still not considered a new method, it's the same method but with different behavior
that is see, the signature is exactly the same as was in human wide eat and wide walk without
parameters that return type being same as well and this is now said to be the overriding
method in the subclass and this is said to be the overridden method in the super type,
that is method overriding and what does that mean is that now see Sneha still doesn't
change the choice like Rangit and that's perfectly fine, overriding is a choice but Shweta
does that with eat and walk but doesn't do with breathe and now you would see when I
say Rangit or breathe and eat and walk you'll get the generic way because Rangit is an ordinary
human, right?
Doesn't have its own way of eating, breathing and walking walks, eats and breathe in the
way every human does and that's perfectly all right but Shweta breathes in the way of
a human does the generic way but walks and eats in her own particular way and if you call
that I'll say now Shweta dot eat as well have a look at this, this would be generic but
these would be Shweta's own logic of how she wards, Shweta's own perspective of how
she eats and with Sneha dance that is a different question we had a look at that previously
but let's focus on these two I'll hit, run again, this was eat, it's gone around this
and just observe this, humans breathe and eat, walk with Rangit still one dimensional, humans
breathe with Shweta dot breathe when we call that but Shweta's own way of eating, Shweta's
own way of walking did walk come or not and you see we said Shweta breathe Shweta eat
and we missed that, let's call that dot walk, now run this and have a look at this, own
style of walking, own way of eating but Shweta can dance in her own way and Sneha now can dance
in the way Shweta does, unless Sneha what does it, she do, she override stance, see?
Inherited dance from Shweta that is Sneha but she decided to override that as well, right
and that is Sneha's own way of dancing, that makes her unique, that makes her special,
you run this and now see that as well, that is the beauty of, that's a two proverb of inheritance
not like in the last example that was just as a starter program but this is where it makes
more sense now, everyone of us has the same methods as the human class has but we have a
choice to define our own behavior, our own way of implementing them but it's still a choice
you saw that some of them took it, others didn't, that is method over riding to you right
and the super time method is called the over ridden method, the subclass method is then called
the over riding method right, so in the next video we'll just go into some details about
overriding what are those exceptional scenarios we tackle one of them and then and as we
cover more concepts, I would keep reminding about a few other exceptional scenarios where
the signature of the two methods would be different but it would still be overriding but
in the majority of the cases for overriding to work first inheritance has to work and for
overriding to work the super class method and the subclass method has to have the same signature
or the overwhelming situations.